Inventory of the Paul B. Ryan papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul B. Ryan papers
1850-1987
1940-1985
78010
Hoover Institution Archives
56 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (22.8 linear feet)
The papers of Paul B. Ryan, an American historian and retired United States Navy Captain, consist of clippings, reports, studies, other printed matter, notes, correspondence, writings, speeches, and photographs relating to Ryan's research on the 1978 Panama Canal treaty, the development of the United States Navy since World War II, the Iran hostage crisis, and Ryan himself.
Ryan, Paul B.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978, with increments received from 1979 to 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Paul B. Ryan, 1913-1987, was a captain in the United States Navy, a historian, and a research fellow at the Hoover Institution. He received a BS from the US Naval Academy in 1936, a master's degree in international relations from Stanford University, and a master's degree in history from San Jose State University. His time in the Navy included combat in World War II, three commands at sea, two tours of duty at the Pentagon, and service as US Naval Attaché for the US embassies in Havana, Cuba and Port-au-Prince, Haiti. He also served as Deputy Director of Naval History in the Department of the Navy from 1969-1972. As a Hoover scholar and historian he published multiple books, including The Panama Canal Controversy: U.S. Diplomacy and Defense Interests (1977), First Line of Defense: The U.S. Navy Since 1945 (1981), and The Iranian Rescue Mission: Why It Failed (1985). In 1987 he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Navy League of the United States for his writings on naval history.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Paul B. Ryan papers consist of clippings, reports, studies, other printed matter, notes, correspondence, and writings broadly related to the Panama Canal and the 1978 Canal Treaty, the United States Navy post-World War II, the Iran hostage crisis, and Ryan himself.
Ryan organized and labeled his research materials based on subject, and from these six series were created, which were then further subdivided by topic; as a result, related materials are not necessarily located together. The Biographical File includes personal files, reports, and educational documents related to Ryan. Correspondence is organized chronologically and by topic. The Panama Canal Controversy Research Materials File, the First Line of Defense Research Materials File, and The Iranian Rescue Mission Research Materials File include materials gathered for use by Ryan when writing his books, as well as his notes. Finally, the Photographs file includes photographs and negatives largely related to the US Navy, as well as some related to the Panama Canal and the Iran hostage crisis.
United States. Navy.; Panama Canal.; Panama--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Panama.; United States--Military policy.
- Biographical File, 1940, 1956-1986
  - Articles and talks by Paul B. Ryan, 1980-1986 (Box 45, Folder 13)
  - Articles by Paul Ryan, published in book and journal [re Diego Garcia base], 1984 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Documents on learning French, 1947 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Educational documents, 1960-1970 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Fitness reports, 1956 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Fitness reports, 1956-1965 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Personal files, 1956-1967, 1972
    - 1956-1958 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - 1957 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - During tenure as Deputy Director of Naval History, Navy Department, 1972 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Personal records and documents, 1969-1977 (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Speeches by Paul B. Ryan, 1961-1981 (Box 52, Folder 1-2)
  - Transcripts, 1965-1966 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - USAF History Symposium, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - USN master's program, 1960-1964 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Veteran's Administration documents, 1961-1969 (Box 51, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1942-1987
  - undated (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - 1959 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - 1969-1972 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - 1971-1981 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - 1972 (Box 51, Folder 10)
  - 1972-1974 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - 1972-1985 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - 1973-1975 (Box 45, Folder 18)
  - 1973-1985 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - 1974-1978 (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
  - 1974-1981 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - 1974-1982 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - 1975 (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - 1975-1977 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - 1975-1984 (Box 36, Folder 1, 6)
  - 1976-1981 (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - 1977-1980 (Box 36, Folder 7, Box 45, Folder 14)
  - 1978-1980 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 36, Folder 9, Box 45, Folder 15)
  - 1979-1985 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - 1980 (Box 37, Folder 4, Box 55)
  - 1981 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - 1981-1984 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - 1981-1986 (Box 36, Folder 5, Box 44, Folder 10)
  - 1982-1986 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - 1983-1986 (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 36, Folder 2, Box 46, Folder 5)
  - 1984-1986 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - 1985 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and documents relating to Paul B. Ryan, 1952-1960 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and mailing lists, undated (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and news, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and news, 1970-1980 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and personal files, 1959-1960 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and printed materials relating to USS Helena, 1953-1959 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and printed materials, 1958-1960 (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and printed materials, 1965-1972 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and printed materials [re Panama], 1976-1979 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and publications, 1987 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and publishing information, 1978 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and read list, 1974-1975 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and research on submarine warfare in WWII, 1942-1985 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - During tenure as USS Union Commanding Officer, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Form 44 Control correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Post-publication correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Re: The First Line of Defense (book), 1981-1982 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Relating to Iran hostage crisis, 1981 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Scribner's, 1972-1974 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - SECNAV, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 7)
- The Panama Canal Controversy Research Materials File, 1850-1983
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of publications, clippings, and Ryan’s research materials related to his book on the Panama Canal, including information on its efficacy, strategic importance, and the treaties between the United States and Panama relating to the Canal Zone; Naval War College assessments of the situation in the Canal Zone; and the canal during the Cold War.
  - Background on Panama and the Canal, 1966-1979
    - Background on Canal, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Canal transits, 1966-1976 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Description of Canal and Panama, 1976-1977 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - History of Panama, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Legal interpretations of the Panama Canal Zone, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Oil and the Canal, 1976-1977 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Panama Canal issue, 1976-1979 (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - Political aspects of the Panama Canal, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - General research materials, 1960, 1965, 1974-1977
    - 1956 Suez crisis, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Government correspondence, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Intelligence papers on terrorism, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Maritime strategic choke points, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      "Strategic Waterways," Naval War College Review, XII, no. 7, March 1960 (marked on cover, though the article itself has been torn out).
    - Suez Canal documents, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Terrorism in revolutionary warfare, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Individuals, 1965-1978
    - Arnulfo Arias, Panamanian President, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Bendetsen report, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - William Buckley on the Canal, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker biographical data, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Jimmy Carter viewpoint and news on Canal, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Fidel Castro, 1975-1977 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Fidel Castro, documents and news clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Congressional opinion letters, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Donald Dozer briefing on the Canal, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Eisenhower on Panama, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Maj. Gen. Robert Fleming, U.S. Army briefing on the Canal, 1968-1975 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Phillip Harman, 1968-1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Kissinger and Gov. George Wallace meeting on Panama, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Sol Linowitz, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Ambassador John C. Mundt, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Ronald Reagan interview on the Canal, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Ronald Reagan on Canal issues, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 23, Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Ronald Reagan viewpoint on Canal, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Soviet views on Panama, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Torrijos background information, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Torrijos biographical data, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Torrijos in Cuba, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - General Wedemeyer analysis, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Biographies of American Canal officials, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Governors of the Canal Zone, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - List of US Naval Commandants in the Panama Canal Zone, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Organization of American States Secretary General, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Latin America materials, 1960-1977, 1983
    - Articles on Latin America, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Brazil, Argentina, Venezuela, 1975-1977 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Castro's Cuba, 1983 (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Communism in Latin America, 1975-1976 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Latin America news digests, 1968 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Latin America news and documents, 1973-1976 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Latin American dictatorship, 1960-1976 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Latin American terrorism, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Moscow's line on Panama and Latin America, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - US-Latin American relations, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Maps, 1976-1977
    - Canal maps and charts, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Cartoons and maps, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Maritime chokepoints, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Panama, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Panama Canal, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notes and bibliographies, 1971-1978
    - Bibliography of the Panama Canal, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Bibliography on Panama and correspondence, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Bound copies of background notes documents from Senate Subcommittee hearings on the Panama Canal, 1971-1977 (Box 7)
    - Journals and research notes on Panama, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Hoover Institute publication materials, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Overview of Hoover book on Panama Canal controversy by Paul Ryan.
    - Notes from Congressional hearings on Panamanian relations and the Panama Canal, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Proposed structure of Panama Canal book, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Research notes and correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Research notes and papers, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Panama Canal Company, 1976, undated
    - Description, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Annual report, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Public relations documents, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Pressure group documents, 1975-1978
    - Anti-treaty, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Canal treaties, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Pressure group documents, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Pro-human rights, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Pro-Panamanian government, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Utterances of organized pressure groups, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Printed matter, 1940, 1959-1979
    - AEI News Digest, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - AEI News Digest, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Armed Forces Journal, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Armed Forces Journal clippings, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - British Weekly Journal clippings, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Christian Science Monitor clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Christian Science Monitor clippings, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 10, Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Congressional Record and statements, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy papers, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Latin America Newsletter clippings, 1974-1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Los Angeles Times articles and notes, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Los Angeles Times clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Los Angeles Times clippings, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Miami Herald, 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - New York Times articles on the Panama Canal, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - New York Times clippings, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - New York Times clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Newsweek articles, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Newsweek clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Newsweek clippings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Palo Alto Times clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Palo Alto Times clippings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Panama Canal Company Daily Digest, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Panama Canal Company Daily Digest, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Panama Canal Company Daily Digests, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Philadelphia Evening Bulletin clippings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Retired Officer Journal, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Retired Officer Journal clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 7, Box 16, Folder 14)
    - San Francisco Chronicle articles on the Panama Canal, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - San Francisco Chronicle clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
    - San Francisco Chronicle and Examiner clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - San Francisco Chronicle and Examiner clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - San Francisco Examiner clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - San Francisco Examiner clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - San Jose Mercury News clippings, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Seapower, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 12)
      Magazine published by the Navy League.
    - Seapower, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Time clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Time clippings, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - U.S. News and World Report clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - U.S. News and World Report clippings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 19, Box 14, Folder 4)
    - U.S. News and World Report news on Canal, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Wall Street Journal clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Wall Street Journal clippings, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Washington Post clippings, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Washington Post clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 9, Box 16, Folder 7)
    - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research documents and news, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Anti-US press on Canal issues, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Article on US Army in Panama, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Articles on Panama and the Canal, 1962-1977 (Box 17, Folder 18-19)
    - Assorted press stories, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Books on Panama, Soviet aggression, and the Panama Canal, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Comptroller General report to Congress, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Department of State documents, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Documents on naval readiness in Canal Zone, 1974-1978 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Documents on Panama Canal from Carter Administration, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Excerpts from books on the Panama Canal, 1959-1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Foreign Broadcast Information Service news, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Foreign Broadcast Information Service news, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Foreign Broadcast Information Service news on the Panama Canal, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Heritage Foundation report, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - International Conference Third World clippings, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Journal articles, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Journal articles and book excerpts on the Panama Canal controversy, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Journal articles on the Panama Canal Zone, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - News and Panamanian foreign communiques, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - News and papers on Canal debates, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - News and State Department documents, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - News articles on Ford and the Panama Canal, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - News articles on US-Panama relations, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - News clippings and speeches on the Canal, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - News clippings on the Canal, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - News clippings on Canal transfer, 1976-1978 (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
    - News clippings on Canal Zone, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - News, correspondence, and documents regarding the Canal, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - News of Carter/Canal discussions, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Official reports on events in Panama, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Panama Canal news and reports, 1976-1979 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Panama news dispatches, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Printed materials [re Panama], 1965 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - US State Department publications, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Various articles on the Canal, 1972-1976 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Various news clippings, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Speeches and statements, 1938, 1966-1977
    - Panama's public statements, 1972-1976 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Pentagon statements, 1975-1976 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Speech about the Canal by US Army Officer, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Speeches and legislation by Representative Daniel Flood of Pennsylvania, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Speeches and public statements about the Canal, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - State Department public statements on Panama Canal, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Statement to Senate by Ryan re Panama Canal treaties, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Studies and statistics, 1968-1978
    - Congressional hearings and studies, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Economic studies on Canal Company, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - International Research Association economic studies, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Naval War College theses, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Panama census, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Panamanian national data and statistics, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Public opinion polls on Panama Canal, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Stanford Research Institute study, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Studies and charts on Panama, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Studies on toll statistics, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Traffic statistics, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - US Army research studies, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Trade and finances, 1975-1976
    - US loans and grants to Panama, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - US overseas loans and grants, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - World trade and the United States, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Treaties and related materials, 1850-1983
    - Analysis and testimony on Panama Canal treaties, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Karl Bendetsen on the Canal treaties, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Congressional opinions on treaties, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Documents on Canal Treaty, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Journal articles on Panama Canal treaties, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letters and position statements by the US Department of State re Panama Canal treaties, 1977-1983 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Opinion pieces on Panama Canal Treaty, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - News from treaty discussions, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - News, notes, and correspondence with regards to Canal Treaty, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - News on Canal treaty debates, 1976-1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Panama Canal treaty copy, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Panama Canal treaties, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Panamanian treaties, 1850-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Panamanian and US documents on Canal Treaties, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Research materials on 1978 Panama-US Canal Treaties, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Statement on Panama Canal treaties by Chairman of the Canal Company, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Teller paper on Canal Treaty, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - US Navy public statements against Panama Canal treaties, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - US-Panama Canal treaties, 1904-1955 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - US State Department - Canal Treaties, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - "Will the Canal Treaties Work?,", 1978 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      In folder titled "Paul Ryan papers."
- First Line of Defense Research Materials File, 1882-1986
  Consists of publications, clippings, and Ryan's research materials related to his book on the US Navy, including information on military history, foreign relations, and strategic plans of the US Navy, particularly in regards to winning a hypothetical conflict with the Soviet Navy.
  - Defense spending, 1971, 1978-1981
    - Assessing defense spending, 1979 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Carter and naval budget, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Congressional Budget Office - Naval peacetime presence mission, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Congressional Budget Office - Navy budget issues, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - "The Fiscal Year 1981 Defense Budget: An Analysis," (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - "The FY 1980-1984 Defense Program: Issues and Trends," Lawrence J. Korb (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Inflation and defense, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - NATO and US defense budget, 1980 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Navy budget 1980-1984 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - The Navy budget process, Force Levels, Captain Amme, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - SECDEF Brown on FY 1980 defense budget, 1979 (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Social programs v. US defense budget, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Department of Defense, 1973-1984
    - Budget and NATO, 1979 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Department of Defense and the US Navy, 1978 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - "Department of Defense Annual Report, Fiscal Year 1979,", 1978 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - "Department of Defense Annual Report, Fiscal Year 1980,", 1979 (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Excessive civilian control in Pentagon, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - "Gigantism" in Department of Defense, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Organizational problems, 1978 (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Reorganizing Pentagon, Steadman-Ignatius studies, circa 1978 (Box 21, Folder 15)